Guide to the Alphonse Louis Pinart Native American Vocabularies
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Native American vocabularies
1646-1789
WA MSS S-285
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.5
(6 boxes)
Chiefly Native American vocabularies in French and Spanish, most of which were created or transcribed by Alponse Louis Pinart. Also includes a few vocabularies for West African languages.
Pinart, A. L. (Alphonse Louis), 1852-1911
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Robertson Coe.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Alponse Louis Pinart (1852-1911), French linguist, traveled in America collecting vocabularies for various Indian languages for publication. The papers consist chiefly of Native American vocabularies in French and Spanish, most of which were created or transcribed by Alponse Louis Pinart. The collection also includes a few vocabularies for West African languages.
African languages -- Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Catechisms; Indians of Central America -- Languages; Indians of North America -- Languages; Indians of South America -- Languages; Africa, West -- Languages; Linguists; Innokentiĭ, Saint, Metropolitan of Moscow and Kolomna, 1797-1879; Berlioz, Alexandre, bishop, 1852-1929; Dudley, Robert, Sir, 1574-1649; Hall, Alfred J. (Alfred James), 1853-1918; Lecombe, Albert, 1827?-1911; Lemmeus, J. I.; Llisa, Pedro de, Fray; Montoya, Francisco; Orbigny, Alcide Dessalines d', 1802-1857; Ortíz, Josef Anselmo; Paredes, Joaquin de; Pinart, A. L. (Alphonse Louis), 1852-1911; Rivera, Antonio de; Urbano, Alonso; Vivero, Feliciano Antonio; Composeco Lorenzana, Josef de; La Fuente Alvarez, Juam José de; Morales y Austina, Nicolas de; Ruano Suarez, Alberto
- Box and Folder List
  Scope and Contents
  Note: All works listed are by Alphonse Louis Pinart unless otherwise indicated.
  - Lenguas Indigenas de la Baja California. Documentos y vocabularios extratos de varios autores publicados nuevamente., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vocabulaires des Differents Dialectes Cowitchin (Ile de Vancouver? Riviere Frazer? etc). Publiées d'apres des travaux divers par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Moreno, arreglado y puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - San Joaquin, Joaquin de. Vocabulario de la lengua Ceona, escrita por el Padre Joaquin de San Joaquin, misionero. Sacado de dos ms. del siglo pasado y dado a luz pro primera vez por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Jicaque, sacado de varios compiladores y arreglado segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vocabularios de los lenguas indigenas de la Alta California.
    - I. Lenguas de la mision de San Carlos de Monterey. Lenguas de la familia Mutsun. Lenguas de la familia Yokut., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - II. Lenguas de la familias de Santa Barbara, San Antonio, Aomo, Shasta y Achomawi., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - III. Lenguas de la familia Patwin - Wintum, Maidu, Nishinam y Niwok., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - IV. Familias Karok, Yurok, Klamath, Chimasiko, Wishok, Yuki., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - V. Familias Numa y Yuma., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Vocabulario de la lengua Seri de los indios de la isla de Tiburon por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Vocabulaire Français-Thlinkit (dialectes de Sitka et Stikine)., undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Catecismo en Lengua Cunacuna. Ms de la biblioteca de Sr. Don Jose Rufino Cuervo., undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Llisa, Pedro de, fray. Pequeño Catecismo Cristiano en la lengua de los indios del Darien, por el R.P. fray Pedro de Llisa, M. Cap., revista por los S.S. Don Alfonso Pinart y Don Tomas J. Carranza., undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Vocabulaire de Jargon Chinook, accompagné d'un recueil de prieres. Publié d'apres un Ms de la Bibliothèque National par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Vocabularios de la lengua Apache, recopilados por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lacombe, Albert. Petit vocabulaire de la langue des indiens Pieds-Noirs, gens du sang et piegans, recueilli par le R.P. A. Lacombe, O.M.F. et les missionaires oblats de Marie Immaculée; publié par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vocabulaires des dialectes Eskimos Occidentaux (Mer de Bering et Ocean Glaciale)., undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bible. Eskimo. Selections. Traduction biblique en langue Eskimo., undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Translated by A. L. Pinart?
  - Tabieu. Vocabulaire en langue Banda (Haut Oubanghi); dialectes du Togbo - Gobu - Langbaire par le Frere Tabieu., undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Comp. by A. L. Pinart.
  - Essai de grammaire Masaie; Vocabulaire Français-Masaie; Vocabulaire Masaie- Français., undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Comp. by A. L. Pinart.?
  - Vocabularios de las lenguas indigenas de Los Estados de Nevada y Utah, de la familia Numa-Uta-Shoshone. Recopilados y publicados por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Vivero, Feliciano Antonio. Vocabulario Breve Castellano - Zoque, formado en Tuxtla a 3 de Febrero de 1789 por el R.P. fray Feliciano Antonio Vivero., 1789 Feb 3 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Camposeco Lorenzana, Josef de. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Mam, formado en Istahuacan a Marzo de 1789 por el P. fray Josef de Camposeco Lorenzanz. Arreglado y puesto de bajo el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Mar (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Padres, Joaquin de. Vocabulario Breve Castellano - Cakchiquel, formado en Teepan, Guatemala, en 1789 por el P. Joaquin de Paredes. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Vocabulario Breve Castellano - Quiche - Cacchipokonchi, formado por los P.P. de St. Domingo., 1789 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Morales y Astina, Nicolas de. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Tzotzil, formado en el pueblo de San Andres a 27 de Enero de 1789 por el R.P. fray Nicolas de Morales y Astina, arreglado y puesto sobre el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Jan 27 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Vocabulario breve de las lenguas Cabecar y Viccita, escrito en 1789 por los P.P. de Colegio de Cristo Crucificado de Guatemala. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Terraba, formado en 1789 por los P.P. del Colegio de Cristo Crucificado de Guatemala, publicado ahora A. L. Pinart. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Tzendal, formado en 1789 por un anonimo, nuovamente arreglado y publicado por A. L. Pinart. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Vocabulario Chinook., undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - [Vocabularies of various Pueblo Indian dialects], undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Orbigny, Alcide Dessalines d'. Vocabularios de las lenguas Itonama y Ytene y confesionario en lengua Itonama, sacados de los papeles de A. d'Orbigny y publicados A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lemmeus, J. I. Vocabulaire de dialectes Kwakiool recueillis par Msgr. J. I. Lemmeus et d'autres investigateurs, suivis d'un court vocabulaire de la langue Bilhoola. Publiés par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Vocabulaires de la langue Aht de la côte ouest de Vancouver. Publiés par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Hall, Alfred James. Notes grammaticales sur la langue Kwagiutl (Kwakiool) par le Reverend Alfred Hall à Alert Bay., undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Vocabulaires Divers., undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Vocabularies of various northwest coast dialects compiled from different sources.
  - Orbigny, Alcide Dessalines d'. Vocabularios de las lenguas Canichana, Cayuvava, Chacara, Movima, Muchojene, Pacaquara, Sarabeca y Curiminaca del departamento del Beni, etc. En la Republica de Bolivia, estraidos de los manuscritos de Alcide d'Orbigny y ahora publicados [por] A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Rivera, Antonio de. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Chanabal formado en Comitan (29 de Enero de 1789) por el R.P. fray Antonio de Rivera y ahora puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Jan 29 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Orbigny, Alcide Dessalines d'. Vocabulario de la lengua Mathaguaya Bejosa o Macatay. Sacado de los papeles manuscritos de Alcide d'Orbigny por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Ruano Suarez, Alberto. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Chorti, ahora puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., [1897] (Box 4, Folder 41)
    "El presente vocabulario fue publicada ... en la obra de ... Alberto Mimbreño titulada Honduranismos, Tegucigalpa, 1897, a quien lo comunico ... Alberto Ruano Suarez."
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Pokoman, formado en 1789 por un autor anonimo, ahora publicado por A. L. Pinart. (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Ortiz, Josef Anselmo. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Subina, formado por el P. fray Joseph Anselmo Ortiz en Zocoltenango a 10 de Febrero de 1789. Arreglado y puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Feb 10 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - La Fuente, Alvarez, Juan Jose de. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Chol, formado en el pueblo de Tila 26 de Enero 1789 por el R.P. fray Juan Jose de la Fuente Albarez. Publicado por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Jan 26 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Montoya, Francisco. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Chiapaneco, formada en Chiapa a 27 de Febrero de 1789 por el R.P. fray Francisco Montoya. Arreglado y puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., 1789 Feb 27 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Pinart, Alphonse Louis, ed. Recueil de prieres de l'église orthodoxe russe traduites dan le dialecte Aglagmiute de Nushagak et du Kushkokvine, Mer de Behring, Alaska. Transcrit et revu par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Innokentii, metropolitan of Moskow. Catechisme et essais d'enseignement Chretien avec les prieres de l'église orthodoxe russe traduits en langue Aleaute d'ounalaska et des notes répondants au dialecte a'Atkha, par les P.P. J. Veniaminoff et J. Netsvietoff. Transcrit et revu par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Pub. 1840 with title: Nachatki kristianskago uchenie.
  - Berlioz, Alexandre, bp. Petit Catechisme Ainu, traduit par Msgr. Berlioz, Eveque d'Hakodati; transcrit et publié par A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Sumus, arreglado y puesto segun el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Pinart, Alphonse Louis, ed. Pequeño Vocabulario Castellano - Pupuluca, formado en 1789 por un padre anonimo; arreglado y puesto por el orden alfabético por A. L. Pinart. (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Dudley, Robert, Sir, styled Duke of Northumberland and Earl of Warwick. Vocabularios de lenguas Americanas y de la de Madagascar sacados de la importante obra de Dudley, Duque de Northumberland, y pulicados novamente por A. L. Pinart., undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
    From his Dell'Arcano del Mare, 1646.
  - Vocabularies of Tinneh Alaska Indians, from various sources., undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Vocabulaire Nanba ou Fagnia ... accompagné d'autres documents Africaines., undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Urbano, Alonso. Arte breve de la lengua Otomi, compuesto por el P. fray Alonso Urbano de la orden de N. P. S. Agustin., undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Additional unsorted vocabularies [in English, French and Spanish]., undated (Box 5, Folder 55-63)
  - Additional unsorted vocabularies [in English, French and Spanish]., undated (Box 6, Folder 64-70)